<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rh:help xmlns:rh="http://www.r-project.org/help" xmlns:r="http://www.r-project.org" 
         xmlns:s3="http://www.r-project.org/S3" xmlns:s4="http://www.r-project.org/S4" 
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" created="2009-02-27 10:06:18">
  <rh:topic>getDocLocation</rh:topic>
  <rh:title>Find the chapter, section, sub-section, etc. of a node</rh:title>
  <rh:description>
    <para>This function allows the caller to find the context of a node within the document. 
  The idea is that she has identified a node having some characteristic of interest, e.g. 
   a link to Web site, a bibliographic reference, a typo.  She wants to be able to locate
  that relative to the document hierarchy, i.e. the chapter, section, subsection and so on.
</para>
    <para>This function can return the nodes, the titles or the numbers of the
 chapter and sections to provide different "views" of this information.
</para>
    <para>Note that we can use <r:func pkg="XML">findXInclude</r:func> to identify the 
   file containing this actual node. We can also use <r:func pkg="XML">getLineNumber</r:func>
   to find the exact line in that file.  This function  <r:func>getDocLocation</r:func>
  is more concerned with understanding where the node is in the overall document, and not within a
  file.
   </para>
  </rh:description>
  <rh:arguments>
   <rh:arg id="node"><para>the <s3:class>XMLInternalNode</s3:class> object whose context is to be found.
</para></rh:arg>
   <rh:arg id="style"><para>one of <r:str>"nodes"</r:str>, <r:str>"titles"</r:str> and <r:str>"position"</r:str>.
  This controls what is returned.
</para></rh:arg>
   </rh:arguments>
  <rh:value>
    <para>The value depends on the value of <r:arg>style</r:arg>. If this is 
      <r:str>"nodes"</r:str>, the result is a list of the matching section and chapter nodes.
     If <r:arg>style</r:arg> is <r:str>"titles"</r:str>, the result is a character
    vector giving the titles of the subsections, sections and chapters.  
    The character vector has names identifying the XML elements, i.e. section and chapter.
    Finally, for <r:str>"position"</r:str>, the value is an integer vector giving the
    numbers of the subsection, section, and chapter, again as a named vector.
     </para>
  </rh:value>

  <rh:seealso>
  </rh:seealso>
  <xi:include href="/Users/duncan/authorInfo.xml" xpointer="xpointer(/*/author)"/>
  <rh:references>
This uses <ulink url="http://www.w3.org/TR/xpath">XPath</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.xmlsoft.org">libxml2</ulink>.
   </rh:references>

  <rh:examples>
    <r:init/>
    <rh:example id="">
      <rh:title> </rh:title>
      <rh:description>
        <para>
	</para>
      </rh:description>
      <r:code>
	</r:code>
    </rh:example>
  </rh:examples>
  <rh:keywords>
    <rh:keyword/>
  </rh:keywords>
  <rh:versionIntroduced version=""/>
</rh:help>
